Guide to the New Day Films Archive, 1969-2018 RL.10180
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Digital Films Collection, 1971-2018; 12 Terabytes 214 digital files
  - Richter, Robert
    - Leaving Home, 2011; 72 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0076_u, Video-file RichterRobert_Leaving Home.mp4)
      Renu, a teenager in Rankhandi—a north India village, plans to be a big city teacher. Instead, after traditional marriage she must move to her husband's village. Women talk frankly about love, sex, marriage, abuse—and women's rights. Anthropologist Mike Mahar, intermittently living in Rankhandi over 50 years, guides us. Produced by Robert Richter.
    - The Ultimate Wish, 2012; 40 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0076_u, Video-file RichterRobert_TheUltimateWish.mp4)
      Moving, unforgettable living witnesses who survived two of the world's most momentous radiation crises: Nagasaki in 1945 and Fukushima in 2011.They are interlaced with nuclear experts and archival footage, some shocking, illuminating the largely unrecognized connection between nuclear weapons and nuclear power, and the growing global movements to abolish both. Produced by Robert Richter, Kathleen Sullivan.
  - Rigby, Theo
    - A Sentence Apart, 2009; 11min (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0077_u, Video-file RigbyTheo_ASentenceApart.mp4)
      The U.S.A. imprisons more people, per capita, than any country in the world. Behind 2.4 million prisoners lies an infinite ripple effect of incarceration on the family and community. A Sentence Apart follows three stories of people coping with a family member in prison, attempting to bridge broken relationships, and diligently working to reverse the generational cycle of incarceration Produced by Jason Sussberg, Theo Rigby.
    - Sin País, 2010; 19 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0077_u, Video-file RigbyTheo_SinPais.mp4)
      In 1992, Sam and Elida Mejia left Guatemala during a violent civil war and brought their one-year old son, Gilbert, to California. The Mejia's settled in the Bay Area, and for the past 17 years they have worked multiple jobs to support their family, paid their taxes, and saved enough to buy a home. They had two more children, Helen and Dulce, who are both U.S. citizens. Two years ago, immigration agents stormed the Mejia's house looking for someone who didn't live there. Sam, Elida, and Gilbert were all undocumented and became deeply entangled in the U.S. immigration system.Sin País begins two weeks before Sam and Elida's scheduled deportation date. After a passionate fight to keep the family together, Sam and Elida are deported and take Dulce with them back to Guatemala.With intimate access and striking imagery, Sin País explores the complexities of the Mejia's new reality of a separated family–parents without their children, and children without their parents. Produced by Theo Rigby.
    - The Caretaker + The Mayor, 2013; 18 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0077_u, Video-file RigbyTheo_TheCaretaker+TheMayor.mp4)
      The Caretaker is a short film about the relationship between an immigrant caretaker and an elderly woman in the last months of her life. Joesy, a Fijian immigrant, works long hours providing live-in care for 95-year-old Haru Tsurumoto. Through intimate and quiet scenes, we explore Joesy's complex relationship with Haru. The two respect one another, because at different times, both have felt like outsiders in the U.S. - Joesy as an undocumented immigrant who fears she could be sent back to Fiji, and Haru as a Japanese American who was sent to the internment camps during World War II. The Mayor is an intimate portrait of a small-town Southern Republican Mayor and his profound and unexpected connection to a mixed-status family of Mexican immigrants. Paul Bridges, the conservative Republican Mayor of Uvalda, Georgia, speaks fluent Spanish and is integrally connected to the Latino immigrant community in his town. Bridges has been a major part of the Hernandez family's life for over a decade and many of the members of the family are undocumented. After the State of Georgia adopts harsh anti-immigrant laws that make it a criminal act to drive or house undocumented people, Mayor Bridges stands up for his community and the Hernandez family both at home, and on the National stage. Produced by Theo Rigby.
  - Rosenstein, Jay
    - In Whose Honor?, 1997; 48 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0078_u, Video-file RosensteinJay_IWH.mp4)
      IN WHOSE HONOR? takes a critical look at the long-running practice of using American Indian mascots and nicknames in sports. It follows the story of Native American mother Charlene Teters and her transformation from a graduate student into a national movement leader, as she struggles to protect Native American cultural symbols and identity for her children as well as generations to come. Produced by Jay Rosenstein.
    - The Lord Is Not On Trial Here Today, 2010; 57 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0078_u, Video-file RosensteinJay_TheLordIsNotOnTrialHereToday.mp4)
      This Peabody Award winning documentary tells the personal story behind the landmark 1948 Supreme Court case McCollum vs. Board of Education, the case that established the separation of church and state in public schools for the first time in U.S. history. Produced by Jay Rosenstein.
  - Sartain, Sophie
    - Mimi And Dona, 2015; 56 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0079_u, Video-file SartainSophie_MimiAndDona.mp4)
      What happens when love runs out of time? For a 92-year-old mother, Mimi, who has cared 64 years for Dona, a daughter who has an intellectual disability, it means facing the inevitable—the likelihood that she will not outlive her daughter and the need to find her daughter a new home.This poignant, heartbreaking and, at times, humorous documentary traces this process through the story of a quirky and deeply connected mother-daughter duo. The film spotlights the challenges of aging caregivers of people with intellectual and developmental disabilities—some 4.6 million Americans, 75% of whom live at home with family—and details the ripple effects of Dona's disability on three generations of a Texas family. Produced by Sofie Sartain.
  - Schiller, Greta
    - No Dinosaurs In Heaven, 2011; 57 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0080_u, Video-file SchillerGreta_NoDinosaursInHeaven.mp4)
      "No Dinosaurs in Heaven" is a lively, enlightening examination of the ongoing battle for America's scientific soul. From the sweeping vistas of the Grand Canyon (where creationist propaganda is on sale in the souvenir shop) to the multi-cultural classrooms of New York City's public schools (where creationist teachers are still refusing to cover the curriculum on evolution – and getting away with it!), the film exposes the subtle, insidious ways in which science education is being hijacked by fundamentalists – claims of religious discrimination and academic repression being their latest tactic. Produced by Greta Schiller.
    - Why Science (DVD Extra), 2011; 7 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0080_u, Video-file SchillerGreta_WhyScienceDVDExtra.mp4)
      A playful intercutting of a 1950's educational film promoting science with science activists in the Grand Canyon. Produced by Greta Schiller.
    - Marion Lake Story, 2014; 27 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0080_u, Video-file SchillerGreta_MarionLakeStory.mp4)
      Shot over 7 years, this is the first film to follow an eco restoration project from inception to completion. From an unsightly, unhealthy lake to a bio diverse habitat for birds and wildlife on the Atlantic Flyway. Produced by Greta Schiller.
  - Seckinger, Beverly
    - Laramie Inside Out (Captions), 2004; 56 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0081_u, Video-file SeckingerBeverly_LaramieInsideOut(Captions).mp4)
      In October 1998, Wyoming college student Matthew Shepard was brutally beaten and left to die. The horror of this murder pushed Laramie into the media spotlight and sparked a nationwide debate about homophobia, gay-bashing and hate crimes. Filmmaker Beverly Seckinger, who grew up in Laramie, was compelled to return to her hometown to see how this event had altered the site of her own closeted adolescence. Along the way she meets "God-hates-fags" Westboro Baptist Church Reverend Fred Phelps, who condemns Shepard and all LGBTQ people to a merciless eternity in hell. But Seckinger meets many more--students, teachers, parents, and clergy--speaking out and taking action.
    - Laramie Inside Out, 2004; 56 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0081_u, Video-file SeckingerBeverly_LaramieInsideOut.mp4)
    - Hippie Family Values, 2017; 64 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0081_u, Video-file SeckingerBeverly_HippieFamilyValues.mp4)
      An intimate chronicle of hippie elders and their adult children, filmed over a 10-year period at a communal ranch in New Mexico. The founders of this back-to-the-land experiment are slowing down and facing declining health. Will the next generation be able to sustain the community?
  - Singh, Harleen
    - Drawn Together, 2018; 52 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0099_u, Video-file SinghHarleen_DrawnTogether.mp4)
      Drawn Together traces the fascinating journey of three comic creators who challenge the notion of race, appearance, and gender stereotypes through cartoons, comics and cosplay.
  - Skurnik, Jonathan
    - A Day's Work A Day's Pay, 2001; 57 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0082_u, Video-file SkurnikJonathan_ADaysWorkADaysPay.mp4)
      A Day's Work, A Day's Pay follows three welfare recipients in New York City from 1997 to 2000 as they participate in the largest welfare-to-work program in the nation. When forced to work at city jobs for well below the prevailing wage and deprived of the chance to go to school, these individuals decide to fight back, demanding programs that will actually help them move off of welfare and into jobs. A Day's Work, A Day's Pay traces the personal and political evolution of its three main characters. Juan Galan successfully organizes WEP workers while battling the demons of his own poverty-stricken childhood. Jackie Marte, who drops out of school in order to raise her two children, tries desperately to stay out of workfare, and in the nick of time succeeds in finding a job-training program that allows her to leave welfare for good. Jose Nicolau overcomes his timidity as he learns to organize against workfare, inspiring his peers with impassioned speeches, and testifying to the City Council about sexual harassment of WEP workers. As the film tracks the three-year effort to pass two critical pieces of legislation, viewers will come to understand the real-life impact that social policy has on human beings. They will also comprehend the effort required for poor and working people to transform themselves from victims of the System to fully empowered citizens who take control of their own lives. Produced by Jonathan Skurnik.
    - Spit It Out, 2005; 55 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0082_u, Video-file SkurnikJonathan_SpitItOut.mp4)
      Spit It Out is a funny and poignant portrait of Jeff Shames' successful efforts to come to terms with his stutter and his family's legacy of denial. Jeff's father is intolerant of and rageful towards his son's imperfections, while his mother never discusses her own childhood stutter. As a teenager, Jeff turns to alcohol and drugs to mask his shame, and eventually marries an alcoholic who interacts with the outside world for him. After his wife gets sober, Jeff discovers the stuttering self-help community and embarks on a healing journey of sobriety, self-acceptance and forgiveness. Produced by Jonathan Skurnik & Jeff Shames.
    - The Elevator Operator, 2006; 8 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0082_u, Video-file SkurnikJonathan_TheElevatorOperator.mp4)
      The Elevator Operator is an intimate portrait of an immigrant forever caught between what he's left behind and his pursuit of the American Dream. Shy and unassuming, Eugene shuttles passengers up and down in a manual elevator while he discusses his work, his emigration from Chernobyl, the joys of fatherhood and his recent US citizenship. In a moment of sadness, he wonders whether leaving his job as a journalist in Kiev was really worth it. Then he reassures himself, revealing his dream that some day his self-published novel will become a Hollywood blockbuster. This poetic snapshot takes students of immigration, labor, sociology, political science, economics, social work and anthropology deep into the heart of the immigrant experience. Produced by Jonathan Skurnik.
    - I'm Just Anneke, 2010; 11 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0082_u, Video-file SkurnikJonathan_ImJustAnneke.mp4)
      Anneke is 12. She loves ice hockey and has a loving, close-knit family. She's also a hardcore tomboy. Everybody who meets her assumes she's a boy. That makes puberty even harder for her than most girls. Anneke's not sure if she wants to be a girl, a boy, or something in-between when she grows up. To give her more time to decide, her doctor has put her on a medication that will suppress the hormones that are causing her body to change before she's ready. Even though she's been rejected by her friends and struggles with depression and suicidal thoughts, Anneke is determined to be her true self. To do that she's decided to maintain a fluid gender identity—she wants to make sure her insides matches her outsides. "I'm Just Anneke" looks into the heart of a new generation of children who don't always fit into a binary conception of gender. Produced by Jonathan Skurnik.
    - The Family Journey, 2010; 14 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0082_u, Video-file SkurnikJonathan_TheFamilyJourney.mp4)
      Raising Gender Nonconforming Children follows the journey of the parents and siblings of young people who are questioning if they're a boy, a girl, or something in between. What about your thinking needs to change? How does your whole family come together to nurture and support them? The frank, vulnerable interviews with families living through this potentially scary transition demonstrate how loving and accepting your gender nonconforming child in the face of ignorance and outright hostility from the community have made them more compassionate human beings. At its heart, it's about how acceptance and unconditional love allow these kids to be who they are and not just survive, but thrive. Produced by Jonathan Skurnik.
    - Badger Creek, 2016; 27 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0082_u, Video-file SkurnikJonathan_BadgerCreek.mp4)
      Badger Creek is a half-hour documentary portrait of a Blackfeet (Pikuni) family, the Mombergs, who live on the lower Blackfeet Reservation in Montana near the banks of Badger Creek. In addition to running a prosperous ranching business, they practice a traditional Blackfeet cultural lifestyle that sustains and nourishes them, including sending their children to a Blackfeet language immersion school, participating in Blackfeet spiritual ceremonies and maintaining a Blackfeet worldview. The film takes us through a year in the life of the family, and through four seasons of the magnificent and traditional territory of the Pikuni Nation. Produced by Randy Vasquez.
    - Becoming Johanna, 2016; 27 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0082_u, Video-file SkurnikJonathan_BecomingJohanna.mp4)
      When Johanna, a 16-year-old transgender Latina, begins her transition and gets kicked out of her home and school, she finds a foster family who loves her and a supportive school principal who helps her graduate and thrive.
    - Creating Gender Inclusive Schools, 2016; 21 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0082_u, Video-file SkurnikJonathan_CreatingGenderInclusiveSchools.mp4)
      What happens when you bring gender training to a public elementary school? In Creating Gender Inclusive Schools the Peralta Elementary School in Oakland CA demonstrates the power of an open and honest conversation about gender. The school brought in the staff of Gender Spectrum to provide training for teachers and administrators as well as an age-appropriate curriculum for students. During this step, everyone involved was empowered to look at their own personal confusion, bias and feelings around gender. Parents are brought into the mix next, and add to the spirited discussion about creating a safe place for all of our children to be themselves. A week of classroom activities helps the students learn about gender, stereotyping, and bullying. Their insightful and intuitive discussions will open your eyes to how comfortable young people can be when given the opportunity to express their thoughts and feelings about gender. Creating Gender Inclusive Schools demonstrates that it's not only possible, but that it's downright fun, to train an entire public elementary school community to be inclusive of transgender and gender expansive youth. Produced by Jonathan Skurnik.
    - The Thick Dark Fog, 2016; 57 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0082_u, Video-file SkurnikJonathan_TheThickDarkFog.mp4)
      Walter Littlemoon attended a federal Indian boarding school in South Dakota sixty years ago. The mission of many of these schools in 1950, was still to "kill the Indian and save the man." The children were not allowed to be Indians – to speak their language or express their culture or native identity in any way at the risk of being severely beaten, humiliated or abused. What effects did these actions cause? Produced by Randy Vasquez.
  - Smith, Tommie Dell
    - Breaking Silence, 1993; 58 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0083_u, Video-file SmithTommieDell_BreakingSilence.mp4)
      Breaking Silence is the definitive film on incest and child sexual abuse. Personal stories told by survivors and their families, woven with telling drawings by abused children, give viewers a realistic understanding of how incest destroys trust and bonding, and limits the lives of its victims. Breaking Silence celebrates survivors who are finding the courage to "break silence" and regain their lives. Translated in 10 languages by educational institutions internationally
  - Somani, Indira
    - Life on the Ganges, 2017; 10 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0100_u, Video-file SomaniIndira_LifeOnTheGanges.mp4)
      In Varanasi, India the boat rides on the Ganges River are part of the spiritual experience and the film introduces the audience to the river, an auspicious event called "Dev Diwali," and one particular boatman, whose main source of strength and survival comes from the Ganges.
  - Son, Mina
    - Making Noise In Silence, 2011; 19 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0084_u, Video-file SonMina_MakingNoiseInSilence.mp4)
      Making Noise in Silence explores the richness and complexities of Deaf culture from the perspective of two Korean high school students who attend the California School for the Deaf, Fremont. Born and raised in South Korea, Jeongin Mun and Min Wook Cho have strong ties to their Korean heritage and learned Korean as their first language. However, what separates Jeongin and Min Wook from most children of immigrant families is that they are also deaf. When their families moved to the United States, their deafness automatically put them into an entirely separate cultural group with its own language, customs, and history. Produced by Mina Son.
  - Sporn, Pam
    - Detroit 48202: Conversations Along a Postal Route, 2018; 82 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0101_u, Video-file SpornPam_Detroit48202ConversationsAlongAPostalRoute.mp4)
      Detroit 48202: Conversations Along a Postal Route examines the rise, demise, and contested resurgence of the City of Detroit through the lens of African- American mail carrier, Wendell Watkins, and the committed community he faithfully served for thirty years.
  - Stern, Susan
    - Barbie Nation, 1998/2007; 53 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0085_u, Video-file SternSusan_BarbieNation.mp4)
      The Barbie doll is not just the world's most popular toy, she's a Rorschach test, revealing attitudes about sexuality, body image, gender roles and creativity. Journeying from Barbie conventions to anti-Barbie demonstrations, from girls' play dates to Barbie web pages, Barbie Nation plumbs the cult of the Barbie doll, telling the Barbie stories of men, women and children. At the center of Barbie Nation is the story of Barbie creator and Mattel co-founder Ruth Handler. Handler's ironic rise and fall brings Barbie Nation to a climax that is about the creation of femininity and the marketing -- and subversion -- of femininity's icon.
    - Self Made Man, 2005; 53 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0085_u, Video-file SternSusan_SelfMadeMan.mp4)
      Is it ever rational to choose death? On Independence Day at Stern Ranch, 77-year-old solar energy pioneer Bob Stern finds out he's seriously ill - possibly dying. Meanwhile, an elderly in-law is dying on artificial life support. Bob decides to cheat that fate and take his own life. His family tries to stop him. Bob sets up a video camera. Daughter Susan Stern (Barbie Nation) explores "rational suicide," the "right-to-die" and the difficult end-of-life choices faced by an aging population.
  - Sterrenberg, Jay
    - Brasslands, 2013; 84 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0086_u, Video-file SterrenbergJay_Brasslands.mp4)
      Brasslands explores the explosive recent popularity of Balkan brass music through the stories of three musicians whose lives revolve around playing the music for very different reasons: a Serbian trumpet master, a virtuosic Roma street musician, and a dedicated American who isn't from the Balkans but has been playing this music in New York for the last 30 years. Their stories all converge at the 50th anniversary of the world's biggest trumpet competition in a hidden valley in Serbia. Created by a unique interdisciplinary filmmaking team of Americans, Serbians, musicians and ethnomusicologists, the film offers an unconventional and unique window into ethnomusicology and Balkan culture. Produced by Adam Pogoff Bryan Chang Jay Arthur Sterrenberg.
    - Stages, 82 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0086_u, Video-file SterrenbergJay_Stages.mp4)
      Stages is a moving and surprisingly funny vérité exploration of the unexpected power of the simple act of storytelling. In New York City's oldest community center, a group of older Puerto Rican women and inner-city youth come together to create an original play out of the stories of their lives. Weaving together themes of immigration, identity, aging and coming of age, Stages offers an intimate portrait of an unlikely ensemble, transformed by the liberating power of their own stories-- first as they are spoken across generations, and later when they are performed for a sold-out show. Produced by Meerkat Media.
  - Syjuco, Marty
    - Give Up Tommorow, 2009; 96 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0087_u, Video-file SyjucoMarty_GiveUpTommorow.mp4)